Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Maria Jolas - Subject Files, 1921-1986; Series X; 4.25; (8 boxes)
  - Société européenne de culture
    - Correspondence and announcements (with notes), 1954-58 (Box 56, Folder 1318)
      Includes: Umberto Campagnolo, Jacques Havet, Jean-Jacques Bernard Paul-Emile Victor
  - Vidal-Naquet, Pierre
    - Clipping, 1983 Mar (Box 56, Folder 1319)
  - Wahl, Jean
    - Memorial service pamphlet, 1975 (Box 56, Folder 1320)
  - Wilde, Oscar
    - "Oscar Wilde at Oxford" by Richard Ellmann, printed version, 1984 (Box 56, Folder 1321)
- Maria Jolas - Personal Papers, 1926-1982; Series XI; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series XI is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Address book, [1941] (Box 57, Folder 1322)
  - Advertisement for Household help, n.d.
  - Affaire Hébert
    - Correspondence, 1939-41, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1323)
    - Financial documents, 1938-40 (Box 57, Folder 1324)
    - Insurance policy, 1938-40
    - Legal documents, 1938, 1940 (Box 57, Folder 1325)
  - Book catalogs, 1943, 1945 (Box 57, Folder 1326)
  - Calendar, 1977-78 (Box 57, Folder 1327)
  - Cantine La Marseillaise
    - Balance sheets, 1945 (Box 57, Folder 1328)
    - Clipping, 1946 Mar
    - Correspondence, 1942, 1945, n.d.
    - Photographs, ca. 1945 (Box 57, Folder 1329)
    - Programs, 1944
    - Stationery, n.d.
  - Clippings
    - La Boisserie, 1979 Apr 22 (Box 57, Folder 1330)
    - Clay, Cassius, 1962 Dec 8
    - Chomsky, Noam and Maria Jolas, 1979 Feb 17
    - "Croyez-vous à la Paix?", 1955 Jan 8
    - Fight for Freedom Committee, n.d.
    - Hemingway, Ernest, 1965 Apr 28
    - Irwin, Laetitia, 1965 Sep
    - Jolas, Jacques, 1957
    - Jonic, Bettina Calder, 1965
    - Mathematics, 1954 Apr 3
    - Sweeney, James Johnson, n.d.
    - Thanksgiving proclamation, 1938 Nov
    - Vosges flood, 1947 Dec 29
    - "The Way of the World" by Kees Van Hoek, 1951 Sep 20
  - Diet Instructions, 1944 Feb 20 (Box 57, Folder 1331)
  - Dog registration certificate, 1941 Dec 24
  - Duthuit, Georges, Lecture advertisement, 1939-40
  - École bilingue de Neuilly
    - Account book, 1939-40 (Box 57, Folder 1332)
    - Advertisements, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1333)
    - Background information, 1938, 1952, n.d.
    - Clippings, ca. 1945 (Box 57, Folder 1334)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1939-49, n.d. (Box 57, Folder 1335-37)
      - [Includes: Paul Léon, Georges Pelorson]
      - Lubienska, H., 1939-40, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1338)
    - Employee reference, 1939-40 (Box 58, Folder 1339)
    - Financial papers, 1934-40 (Box 58, Folder 1340)
    - Insurance policies, 1932-40 (Box 58, Folder 1341)
    - Legal documents, 1937, 1940 (Box 58, Folder 1342)
    - Letters to parents, 1939, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1343)
    - Memos, n.d.
    - Property inventories, 1939, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1344)
    - Radio script, "Six Schoolboy Martyrs", [1945?] (Box 58, Folder 1345)
    - Receipts, 1940
    - Rental contracts, 1935-36 (Box 58, Folder 1346)
    - Report on Stirling-Wendal, [1945?]
    - School policies, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1347)
    - Tax documents
      See: Oversize, Box 68, folder 1589
    - Utilities accounts, 1933-40 (Box 58, Folder 1348)
  - Instruction for Dinner Party, ca. 1954 (Box 58, Folder 1349)
  - Interviews
    By Dillon, Ellis, "The Innocent Muse" James Joyce Quarterly
    - Printed text, 1982 (Box 58, Folder 1350)
    - Response letter from Maria Jolas, draft, 1982
    - By Hayman, David
      - Transcript, 1980 Jul (Box 58, Folder 1351)
      - Photocopy, corrected, 1980 Jul
    - By Kenner, Hugh
      - Transcript, 1977 Jun 14 (Box 58, Folder 1352)
    - By Marder, Irving, International Herald Tribune
      - Clipping, 1980 Jun 17 (Box 58, Folder 1353)
    - Panel Discussion, "Then and Now" Symposium
      - Transcript, English, 1964 (Box 58, Folder 1354)
      - Transcript, French, 1964
      - See also: Series VII, Correspondence - David Davis, Box 29 folder 568
    - By Radio Jerusalem [?] - audiotape
    - By Rosen, Bob, Village Voice
      - typescript carbon, 1970 (Box 58, Folder 1355)
    - By Rousseau, François-Olivier, Les matins du livre
      - Clipping, 1982 Feb 26 (Box 58, Folder 1356)
    - With Sarraute, Nathalie - audiotape, ca. 1970s
      [transferred to Historical Sound Recordings, Sterling Memorial Library]
    - By Smith, Kelly, "Paris is still a home for American Artists" Courier-Journal & Times, Louisville
      - Clipping, 1967 May 28 (Box 58, Folder 1357)
    - By Sollers, Philippe, Libération
      - Clipping, 1982 Nov 26 (Box 58, Folder 1358)
  - Licenses and ID cards, 1940-51 (Box 58, Folder 1359)
  - Marriage certificate, 1926 Jan 12 (Box 58, Folder 1360)
  - Military insignia pamphlet, ca. 1942 (Box 58, Folder 1361)
  - Notes, 1966, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1362)
  - Parking ticket and receipt, 1951 (Box 58, Folder 1363)
  - Passport, 1954 (Box 58, Folder 1364)
  - Power of attorney for James Joyce [signed by Joyce], 1940 (Box 58, Folder 1365)
  - Power of attorney to Emile Jolas, n.d. (Box 58, Folder 1366)
  - Projet de création d'une école secondaire en Europe, outline, 1947 Mar (Box 58, Folder 1367)
  - Receipts, 1940-63 (Box 58, Folder 1368)
  - Ticket stubs, 1944
  - Scrapbook, 1941-72 (Box 58, Folder 1369)
  - Songs - audiotape, 1965
  - Will - Maria Jolas [with letter], 1954 (Box 58, Folder 1370)
  - Will - Betsy B. McDonald [including legal correspondence], 1936 (Box 58, Folder 1371)
- transition - General Office Files, 1926-1964; Series XII; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series XII is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Advertisements, 1927-49 (Box 59, Folder 1372)
  - Clippings, 1932-48 (Box 59, Folder 1373)
  - Contributions
    - Borrow, Anthony [with letter] "The Four Great Beasts" Forum, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1374)
    - "the Great Refusal," typescript carbon, n.d.
    - The Apotheosis of Four Entomologists, typescript carbon, corrected, n.d.
    - Lautréamont, Comte de [Isidore Ducasse] "The Lay of Maldoror (Canto I: Fragment)," typescript carbon, corrected, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1375)
    - Eluard, Paul "Deux chansons de toile: Pour un chant [and] dimanche après-midi," typescript carbon
      [includes letter from Marguerite
      Duthuit to Maria Jolas]
    - Engels, Norbert "Et Mirabilius Reformasti," typescript, n.d.
    - Feibleman, James K. "The Five Functions of Art," typescript [with letter], 1948 Jul 27
    - Fernier, Vincent "the many faces of a house," typescript [with letter], 1948
    - Fitzsimmons, James "Exhibition of Photographic Abstractions and Fantasies" photographs with programs and résumé, 1947
    - [Jolas, Eugène] "Document," typescript, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1376)
    - "Construction of the Imagination," typescript, n.d.
    - "Dream-Poems," typescript, 1925-26
    - "Express," typescript, n.d.
    - Larsson, Raymond E. F. "Five Poems," typescript [with letter], 1948 Mar 12 (Box 59, Folder 1377)
    - M., H.. "Some Remarks on Aragon: Art and Politics in the Totalitarian Era," typescript carbon [with note], 1945 Sep
      [Includes letter to James Stern]
    - Mackay, S. E. "The Thief," typescript, n.d.
    - MacLeod, Norman "Scenario of a Verse Walking," typescript carbon, n.d.
    - McDowall, David "Hands Across the Sea," typescript [with letter], 1948 Jan 28
    - Wood, Elizabeth [all typescript] with letter, 1939 (Box 59, Folder 1378)
    - "It Rained," "Never More" "Look Through the Window, Child" "The Real Value"
    - Orlovitz, Gil [all typescript] with letter, 1948
    - "Nocturnal Showing: City" "On Certain Suspensions "Citizen" "Sonnet"
    - "Trio: Tenderloin Bar" "Sonnet" "Prisoner" "Sonnet" "Sonnet" "Sonnet: On Choices"
    - "Fifth Monolog" "Quick! Telephone the Teleologist" "Sonnet" "Sonnet" "Brio" "Conceive You, Conquerer and Cullion" "Lyric"
    - Robinson, James R. "Brotherhood of Man," typescript [with letter], 1940 Jun 15
    - Wirtz, Warren "Poems After Melville," typescript [with letter], n.d.
    - Unidentified "Tableau," typescript, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1379)
    - "Die Schönheit Schneiden Wie ein Schwert," holograph, n.d.
    - "Monte Casino," holograph, n.d.
    - "Les Louanges ou Paraphrase du Psaume Cent Quarante-Huit," holograph, n.d.
  - Correspondence
    - "A" general, 1947-50 (Box 59, Folder 1380)
    - "B" general, 1941-50
    - Borrow, Antony, 1948-49
    - Brient, Michel, 1949-50, n.d.
    - Broch, Hermann, 1948 Nov 11
    - "C" general, 1937-50 (Box 59, Folder 1381)
    - "D" general, 1940-48
    - Day-Lewis, Cecil, n.d.
    - DeVerry, Ruth, 1937-38
    - Duhamel, Marcel, 1957 Dec 17
    - Duthuit, Georges, 1947-50 (Box 59, Folder 1382)
    - Duthuit, Marguerite, n.d.
    - "E" general, 1937, 1957 (Box 59, Folder 1383)
    - Edel, Leon, 1957 Oct 27
    - "F" general, 1941, 1946
    - Faber & Faber, 1936-47, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1384)
    - "G" general, 1938-47 (Box 59, Folder 1385)
    - Giedion-Welcker, Carola, 1949, 1964
    - Gilbert, Stuart, 1947 Aug
    - Gotham Book Mart, 1939, 1941
    - Greenberg: Publisher, 1941 (Box 59, Folder 1386)
    - Greene, Philip L., 1957
    - "H" general, 1945-50 (Box 59, Folder 1387)
    - Hausmann, Raoul, 1950 Apr
    - "J" general, 1949-50
    - "K" general, 1951, 1961
    - "L" general, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1388)
    - Larsson, Raymond E. F.
      See: Contributions, Box 61 folder 1407
    - Lasky, Melvin, n.d.
    - Laughlin, James, 1937, n.d.
    - "M" general, 1947-50
    - Messageries du Livre, 1938-39, n.d.
    - Motherwell, Robert, 1947 Apr 3
    - "N" general, 1940, 1960 (Box 59, Folder 1389)
    - "P" general, 1940
    - Prescott, Joseph, 1940 Jun 1
    - "R" general, 1947 (Box 59, Folder 1390)
    - Ramnoux, Clémence, 1948-49
    - "S" general, 1938, 1958
    - Stechert-Hafner, Inc., 1940-51
    - Stern, James
      See: Contributions - M., H., Box 61 folder 1429
    - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1937-41 (Box 59, Folder 1391)
    - "T" general, 1940, 1949,n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1392)
    - "V" general, 1945
    - Vanguard Press, 1947-51
      [Includes: Seon Givens]
    - Villiers and Company, 1947
    - "W" general, 1941-57 (Box 59, Folder 1393)
    - Wahl, Jean, 1944 Mar 7
    - Watkins, Vernon, 1947 Aug 31
    - Weightman, J. G., 1948 Jun 2
    - Winters, Yvor, 1948 May 19
    - Unidentified, 1947, 1949,n.d.
  - Financial papers, 1938-52 (Box 59, Folder 1394)
  - Legal papers, 1927-47 (Box 59, Folder 1395)
  - Letterhead and Stationery, [1947] (Box 59, Folder 1396)
  - Notes, 1949, n.d. (Box 59, Folder 1397)
  - Photocopies of printed pages, 1927-35 (Box 59, Folder 1398)
  - Printer's accounts, 1937-49 (Box 59, Folder 1399)
  - Scrapbooks, 1926-54 (Box 60, Folder 1400-01)
  - Subscribers list, ca. 1936 (Box 60, Folder 1402)
  - Shipping accounts, 1938-39 (Box 60, Folder 1403)
  - "Suggestions for a French Enquête", n.d. (Box 60, Folder 1404)
- Transition - Imprints, 1905-1955; Series XIII; 0.75 linear feet (2 boxes)
  Series XIII is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - James Joyce Yearbook
    - Advertisement, [1949] (Box 61, Folder 1405)
    - Clippings, 1948-50 (Box 61, Folder 1406)
    - Contributions
      Broch, Hermann
      - "Joyce and the Present Age," typescripts carbon, corrected, [1936, 1948] (Box 61, Folder 1407)
      - Ford, William J. "James Joyce: An Artist in Adversity," Quarterly Bulletin [of Northwestern Univ Medical School], offprint, 1949 (Box 61, Folder 1408)
      - Frank, Nino "L'Ombre qui avait perdu son homme," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 61, Folder 1409)
      - Gilbert, Stuart Sketch of a Scenario for Anna Livia Plurabelle, typescript carbon, [1948?] (Box 61, Folder 1410)
      - Gillet, Louis "Stele for James Joyce," typescript carbon, corrected [translation by Maria Jolas, [1946, 1948] (Box 61, Folder 1411)
      - Goldman, Bernard Illustration for Ulysses [photograph with letter], 1948 (Box 61, Folder 1412)
      - Koch, Vivienne "James Joyce and the American Scene, 1951," typescript, corrected [with letter] (Box 61, Folder 1413)
      - Jolas, Maria "Documents, Notes, Calendar," typescript carbon, [1948-49] (Box 61, Folder 1414)
      - Jolas, Maria "Forward," typescript carbon, corrected, 1949 Apr (Box 61, Folder 1415)
      - Jolas, Maria "Traduttore... Tradittore?," typescripts, corrected, [1948-49] (Box 61, Folder 1416)
      - Joyce, James "Ad-Writer," typescript carbon, 1932 May 22 (Box 61, Folder 1417)
      - Noël, Lucie [Lucie Léon] "James Joyce," typescript carbon, 1945 (Box 61, Folder 1418)
      - Ramnoux, Clémence "The Finn Cycle," typescript carbons, [1947-48] (Box 61, Folder 1419)
      - Soupault, Philippe "Recollections of James Joyce," typescript, corrected, [1943] (Box 61, Folder 1420)
      - Straumann, Heinrich "Last Meeting with Joyce," typescript carbon, [1948] (Box 61, Folder 1421)
      - Weber, Roland von "On and About James Joyce's Exiles ," typescript carbon, corrected, [1948] (Box 61, Folder 1422)
      - Weidlé, Wladimir "On the Present State of Poetic Language," typescript carbon, corrected [translation with original in Les Cahiers de la Pléiade ], 1947 (Box 61, Folder 1423)
      - Unsigned - "Interview with Mr. John Stanislaus Joyce," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 61, Folder 1424)
      - Unsigned - "Un témoignage poétique ensuite: je l'emprunte au poète irlandais James Joyce..."," typescript (Box 61, Folder 1425)
    - Correspondence
      - Anglo-French Literary Service, 1950-51 (Box 61, Folder 1426)
      - "B" general, 1949-50
      - Brient, Michel, 1949 Dec
        See also: Presses Littéraires de France, Box 61 folder 1432
      - Broch, Hermann, 1948-49
      - Brody, Daniel, 1948-49 (Box 61, Folder 1427)
      - Bussy, Dorothy, 1948-49
      - "C" general, 1948-50
      - Davenport, Guy, 1950 Apr 21 (Box 61, Folder 1428)
      - "F" general, 1948-49
      - "G" general, 1950
      - Gotham Book Mart, 1949-50
      - "H" general, 1948-50 (Box 61, Folder 1429)
      - Hachette, 1950-60
      - Hoek, Kees van, 1950-52
      - Huebsch, B. W., 1948-49
      - "I" general, 1950-51 (Box 61, Folder 1430)
      - "K" general, 1949
      - Koch, Vivienne, 1950-51
      - "L" general, 1949
      - "M" general, 1950-55 (Box 61, Folder 1431)
      - Magny, Claude-Edmonde, 1949
      - Morel, Auguste, 1949 Mar 7
      - "N" general
      - "O" general, 1951 (Box 61, Folder 1432)
      - "P" general, 1950-51
      - Pendleton, Edmund, 1949
      - Prescott, Joseph, 1951 Apr 27
      - Presses Litteraires de France, 1949
      - "R" general, 1949-50 (Box 61, Folder 1433)
      - "S" general, 1949-52
      - Slocum, John, 1948-49
      - Straumann, Heinrich, 1949 (Box 61, Folder 1434)
      - Switzerland, Eidg. Departement des Innern, 1949
      - "U" general, 1950 (Box 61, Folder 1435)
      - Weber, Roland von, 1948-49 (Box 61, Folder 1436)
      - "Y" general, 1950
      - Unidentified, 1951, n.d.
    - Cover mock-ups, 1948-49 (Box 61, Folder 1437)
    - Encyclopedia Britannica article on Joyce by Joseph Prescott [autographed to Nora Joyce], [1947] (Box 61, Folder 1438)
    - Notes, [1948-50] (Box 61, Folder 1439)
    - Notice to collectors, 1949 Jun (Box 61, Folder 1440)
    - Photographs for text, 1932-41, n.d. (Box 61, Folder 1441)
    - Photographs list, 1949 (Box 61, Folder 1442)
    - Reviews, 1950, 1952 (Box 61, Folder 1443)
    - Table of contents, [1948-49] (Box 61, Folder 1444)
  - Novalis ou le romantisme blanc
    - Book wrapper, n.d. (Box 62, Folder 1445)
  - Transition Anthology
    - Contributions
      - Arp, Hans "Notes from a Diary," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1932] (Box 62, Folder 1446)
      - Ball, Hugo - "Fragments from a Dada Diary," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], 1916-17
      - Ball, Hugo - "Gnostic Magic," typescript carbon, 1935
      - Breton, André "Introduction to the Discourse on the Dearth of Reality," English translation, typescript carbons, corrected, [1927]
      - [Brunhes, Jean?] "Vase de Gundestrup," typescript carbon, corrected, 1920 Jan 21
      - Lautréamont, Comte de [Isidore Ducasse] "From the Lay of Maldoror (Canto 1)," English translation by Eugène or Maria Jolas, typescript carbon, [1927]
      - Duthuit, Georges [On André Masson] typescript carbons, corrected
      - Einstein, Carl "Bebuquin," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], 1905-08
      - Eluard, Paul "A Dream," typescript [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1927]
      - Gide, André "Roundelay of the Pomegranate," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1927
      - Gordi, Tooni [all typescript], 1938, 1940
      - "Brightly a Redness" "Tentative Fan" "Dark Ailment" "Question with Answer" "Sadist" "Border-line" "All the boys and girls..." "Conjecture"
      - Guss, Jack "The Gospel According to Jack," typescript carbon, 1948
      - Gustafson, Ralph "Fanfare for Living," typescript carbon [with letter], 1948 Mar 13
      - Hayter, S. W. Photographs of artwork, 1937 (Box 62, Folder 1447)
      - Huelsenbeck, Richard "Dada Lives," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], 1936 Aug
      - Jean Paul [Richter] "Walt's Dream," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1934]
      - Jolas, Eugène "Suggestions for a New Magic," typescript, [1927]
      - Kafka, Franz "The Sentence," typescript carbon, [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1928]
      - Kees, Weldon [all typescript], n.d.
      - "This is the Man" "Preface for an Age" "Window" "Pattern" "Midnight"
      - Lussier, Leonard "Pensions Come with Death," typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 62, Folder 1448)
      - King, Larry "Find---Tomorrow ( A Ballet in Two Movements)," typescript carbon, 1950
      - Leiris, Michel "From the Heart to the Absolute," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1929]
      - Péret, Benjamin "In a Clinch," typescript carbon [translated by Elliot Paul], [1928]
      - Reyes, Alfonso "Tropics," typescript carbon [translated by Marquise d'Elbée], 1925
      - Ribemont-Dessaignes, Georges "He put his hat upon the ground..."," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1927]
      - [Singbery, Mrs.?] [Matisse and Picasso], typescript, corrected
      - Schwitters, Kurt "Anna Blossom has Wheels," typescript carbon, corrected [translated by Myrtle Klein], [1927]
      - Soupault, Philippe "Hymn to Liberty," typescript carbon [translated by Maria Jolas], 1927
      - Tzara, Tristan "The Approximate Man," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1930]
      - Stein, Gertrude "Four Saints in Three Acts," pp. 19-54 typescript carbon, [1929]
      - Werfel, Franz "From a Discourse on the Religious Experience," typescript carbon [translated by Eugène Jolas], [1934]
    - Correspondence, 1949 (Box 62, Folder 1449)
      [Includes: Vanguard Press, Seon Givens]
    - Editorial notes, 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1450)
    - Prospectuses, ca. 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1451)
    - Publishing contract, 1948 Jan (Box 62, Folder 1452)
  - Transition Cahiers
    - Business plan, ca. 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1453)
    - Cover mock-up, ca. 1948
    - Prospectuses, ca. 1948
  - Transition Press
    - Address lists, ca. 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1454)
    - Business plan, ca. 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1455)
    - Prospectuses for works by Eugène Jolas, ca. 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1456)
    - Prospectuses, general, ca. 1948 (Box 62, Folder 1457)
    - Résumés
      - Eugène Jolas, [1947 Jun 30] (Box 62, Folder 1458)
      - Maria Jolas, 1947 JUn 30
  - Transition Stories
    - Dust jacket, [1939] (Box 62, Folder 1459)
  - Transition Word
    - Editorial statement, n.d. (Box 62, Folder 1460)
  - Vertical Yearbook
    - Advertisements, 1941 (Box 62, Folder 1461)
    - Contributors
      - Beaudoin, Kenneth L. "Funk and Wagnall's Statement," typescript, 1942 May 7 (Box 62, Folder 1462)
      - Ireland, Thelma [all typescript]
      - "Well-fed" "Near-sighted" "A Mother's WIll" "Night" "The Viel of Mystery" "Parson Nature"
    - Copyright, 1942 May 16 (Box 62, Folder 1463)
    - Correspondence
      - "B" general, 1940, n.d. (Box 62, Folder 1464)
      - Black Faun Press, 1940-41 (Box 62, Folder 1465)
      - Bonner, Amy, 1941-42
      - Boyle, Kay, 1942
      - "C" general, 1940, 1941 (Box 62, Folder 1466)
      - Colum, Padraic, 1942, n.d.
      - Gotham Book Mart, 1941-47 (Box 62, Folder 1467)
      - Gustafson, Ralph, 1942 Feb 15
      - Hartley, Marsden, [1942?]
      - "N" General - "W" general, 1940-46 (Box 62, Folder 1468)
    - Manifesto notes, ca. 1941 (Box 62, Folder 1469)
- James Joyce - Correspondence, 1920-1940; Series XIV; 0.25; (1 box)
  Series XIV is arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent. An asterisk indicates a typewritten transcript of a letter made by Maria Jolas.
  - Aldington, Richard, 1920-28 (Box 63, Folder 1470)
  - Anderson, Sherwood, 1921 Dec 3
  - Antheil, Georges, 1930 May 3
  - Beckett, Samuel, n.d. (Box 63, Folder 1471)
  - Beran, Felix, 1932 Sep 23
  - Brauchbar, Edmund, 1940 Aug 28
  - Budgen, Frank, 1939 Jul 18 (Box 63, Folder 1472)
    [includes poem: "The Names of Odin"]
  - Cerf, Bennett, 1940
  - Clancy, J. P., 1940 Mar 16
  - Credit Suisse, 1940 (Box 63, Folder 1473)
  - Ford, Ford Madox, 1932 Aug 29
  - Friede, Donald, n.d.
  - Gates, Arnold F., 1940 Feb 2 (Box 63, Folder 1474)
  - Giedion-Welcker, Carola, 1939-40
  - Gillet, Louis, 1931-40 (Box 63, Folder 1475)
  - Greenwood, C. J., 1940 (Box 63, Folder 1476)
  - Greviova, Roberto, 1929 Nov 30
  - Harrison, Leland, 1940 Oct 22
  - Hart, Robert Edward, 1937 Sep 10 (Box 63, Folder 1477)
  - Hielanstadt Burghölzli, 1940 Aug 16
  - Hertz, Wilhelm, 1936 Sep 14
  - Hunt, Leigh J., 1940 (Box 63, Folder 1478)
  - Jolas, Eugène, 1928 Sep 31
  - Jolas, Maria, 1940
  - Joyce, George [Giorgio], 1935 Feb 8
  - Kennon, Michael, 1930 Jul 12 (Box 63, Folder 1479)
  - Larbaud, Valéry, 1921-29
  - Légation d'Irlande, 1940 (Box 63, Folder 1480)
  - Léon, Paul, 1934 Sep 21
  - Lester, Sean, 1940 Dec 13
  - Lewisohn, Ludwig [?], 1936 Sep 20 (Box 63, Folder 1481)
  - Makinsky, A, 1940 Oct 7
  - Medcalf, Albert E., 1932 Jul 1
  - Mercanton, Jacques, 1940 Aug 21 (Box 63, Folder 1482)
  - Ministère de L'Interieur, Vichy, 1940 Dec 7
  - Moore, George _ 1929
  - Murphy, Sean
    See: Legation d'Irlande, Box 63 folder 1480
  - Myers, Rollo, 1939 (Box 63, Folder 1483)
  - O'Casey, Sean, n.d.
  - Ofner, Richard, 1939 Mar 25
  - Oshima, S., 1939 Nov 4 (Box 63, Folder 1484)
  - Parcheminey, Georges, 1939 Jul 3
  - Pettycum, A. M., 1940 Sep 29
  - Pothayska, J., 1926 Oct 26 (Box 63, Folder 1485)
  - Poulossier, M., 1940 Aug 3
  - Pound, Ezra, 1920-31, n.d. (Box 63, Folder 1486)
  - Power, Arthur, 1939 Jan 22 (Box 63, Folder 1487)
  - Le Pré Carré, 1940 Oct 15
  - Presses Universitaires de France, 1940 Apr 17
  - Rogers, Marcello, 1939 May 5 (Box 63, Folder 1488)
  - Ross, Harold, n.d.
  - Roth, Samuel, 1921 Feb 12
  - Ruggiero, P., 1940 (Box 63, Folder 1489)
  - Sax, Sylvia, 1938 May 14
  - Searle, Humphrey, 1940 Apr 8
  - Seward, William, Jr., 1939 Jul 12 (Box 63, Folder 1490)
  - Silvestri, Tullio, 1920-26
  - Slocum, John J., 1940 Sep 9
  - Soupault, Marie-Louise, n.d. (Box 63, Folder 1491)
  - Straumann, Heinrich, 1940 Dec 22
  - Sweeney, James Johnson, 1940 Aug 23
  - Vail, Laurence, 1940 Dec 18 (Box 63, Folder 1492)
  - Wallner, Woodruff - American Embassy, 1940 Sep 17
  - Westrom, A., 1939 Nov 12
  - Zumsteg, Gustav, 1940 Dec 13 (Box 63, Folder 1493)
  - Unidentified - to Joyce, 1940
- James Joyce - Writings, 1904-1949; Series XV; 16
  Series XV is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Anna Livia Plurabelle
    - Background notes on Finnegan and O'Reilly families, [1949?] (Box 64, Folder 1494)
    - Fragment from transition, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1495)
    - French translations by Joyce, Soupault, Goll, Jolas, Beckett, and Peron, typescript carbons with list of corrections, 1932 (Box 64, Folder 1496)
    - French translation fragment by Soupault, typescript carbon, n.d. (Box 64, Folder 1497)